<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Panegyrick on Their Royal Highnesses and congratulating his return from Scotland</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55205</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P264</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11100</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13790528</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13790528</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101833</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55205)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101833)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 470:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Panegyrick on Their Royal Highnesses and congratulating his return from Scotland</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. Godbin and J. Playford for Jos. Hindmarsh ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701 --  Poetry.</term>
               <term>Mary, --  of Modena, Queen, consort of James II, King of England, 1658-1718 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101833:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->
            <p>A PANEGYRICK ON THEIR Royal Highneſſes, And Congratulating His RETURN FROM SCOTLAND.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. Godbid</hi> and <hi>J. Playford</hi> for <hi>Joſ. Hindmarſh</hi> at the Sign of the Black Bull near the Royal-Exchange in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="panegyric">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101833:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 39 -->
            <head>A PANEGYRICK ON THEIR Royal Highneſſes.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHen the Moſt High Eternal Son of God</l>
               <l>Through fam'd <hi>Judea</hi> in Proceſſion rode,</l>
               <l>The Loyal <hi>Publican,</hi> with zealous haſt,</l>
               <l>Climb'd up a Tree to view him as he paſt,</l>
               <l>And with a look that did his Joy relate</l>
               <l>The Mighty Saviour did congratulate:</l>
               <l>So 'mongſt the Crowds that with Impatience ſtrove</l>
               <l>T' expreſs their Fealty and faithful Love,</l>
               <l>I and my throbbing heart with equal flames</l>
               <l>Panted and preſt to greet the Godlike <hi>JAMES.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Welcome then, Mighty SIR; welcome as Peace</l>
               <l>To conquer'd Nations, or to ſick Men, Eaſe;</l>
               <l>Welcome, as what you bring us, <hi>Loyalty,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A fruit which in our Iſle we rarely ſee;</l>
               <l>In th' barren North it blooms, to Storms expos'd;</l>
               <l>But in our Sunny Climate never grows:</l>
               <l>Here fertile Nature makes the Commons Kings,</l>
               <l>And from her fatneſs rank Rebellion ſprings':</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Damn'd luſt of Engliſh-men, that ne're repented</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Their Treaſons, nor with Bleſſings were contented.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:101833:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 40 -->
               <l>Black was the Day, and blaſted was the Year,</l>
               <l>When the curſt Factious, full of wretched fear,</l>
               <l>Sought the <hi>true</hi> Heir of <hi>England</hi> to exclude,</l>
               <l>Only becauſe He was too <hi>great,</hi> and <hi>good,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Two Epithetes that never yet could ſuit</l>
               <l>The ſordid Mind of your true Engliſh Brute:</l>
               <l>Loud Tempeſts roar'd, as if deſign'd to croſs</l>
               <l>The Royal Mandate, and not let Him paſs,</l>
               <l>Whilſt weeping Showers ſeem'd to mourn our loſs:</l>
               <l>And as each Element then bore a part</l>
               <l>In grief, even ſo did every Honeſt Heart.</l>
               <l>But now the happy hours are doubly bleſs't,</l>
               <l>The Land with the full Store of Heaven poſſeſs't;</l>
               <l>The Seaſon ſmiles, and each propitious Ray</l>
               <l>For His Return their ſecret Joy diſplay;</l>
               <l>The flowers that did in private Cloſets keep,</l>
               <l>And during th' Winter of His Abſence ſleep,</l>
               <l>Bloom out, and a gay fragrant Robe put on,</l>
               <l>To bleſs and welcome in the RISING SUN;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Laetamur</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">The Motto of the Medal.</note> is the Word, a word which late</l>
               <l>As mighty Hopes, did mighty Joy create,</l>
               <l>When the fam'd <hi>Motto</hi> with applauſe was put</l>
               <l>To the Effigie of the <hi>Grand Patriot,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Neareſt their hearts, where late their <hi>Georges</hi> hung,</l>
               <l>The pale-fac't Medall with its Silver tongue</l>
               <l>Was plac't, whilſt every Wearer ſtill expreſt</l>
               <l>His Joy to harbour there ſo fam'd a Gueſt.</l>
               <l>The Wretch that ſtampt it got immortal fame;</l>
               <l>'Twas coyn'd by ſtealth, like Groats at <hi>Brumicham;</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101833:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 41 -->
               <l>Whilſt each Poſſeſſor with exalted voice</l>
               <l>Cryes, <hi>England's ſaev'd, and now <hi>Let us Rejoyce.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </l>
               <l>But though Seditious Tenets they purſue,</l>
               <l>We have a Cauſe of Joy ſolid and true,</l>
               <l>And therefore let us cry <hi>Laetamur</hi> too.</l>
               <l>For Mighty <hi>YORK'S</hi> return'd, return'd to Raign</l>
               <l>O're hearts, and move in His Great Sphere again:</l>
               <l>'Tis in His Face you ſee the RISING SUN,</l>
               <l>T'other's a <hi>Comet</hi> blazing o're the Town,</l>
               <l>Portending Miſchiefs ſeeming to explain</l>
               <l>The <hi>former</hi> Tragick Scene deſign'd <hi>again.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Fly then ye Loyal Natives, fly with zeal,</l>
               <l>Embrace His Knees, and your true Joy reveal;</l>
               <l>Prove your affection to your Injur'd Prince,</l>
               <l>Give him your Hearts, for you had his long ſince:</l>
               <l>Give Him your Hearts, oppoſe the Rebel Power,</l>
               <l>And never part with your Lov'd HEROE more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And hail Bright PRINCESS, beſt of thy fair Kind,</l>
               <l>An Angel's Body with an Angel's Mind,</l>
               <l>Beauteous as are the Virgin Saints above,</l>
               <l>That ſit and ſmile on the right hand of <hi>Jove,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And good, as the firſt ſtate Heav'n form'd 'em in,</l>
               <l>E're that Angelick Sex knew how to ſin;</l>
               <l>How when She comes ſhall we our crimes attone?</l>
               <l>How ſhall we meet the Juſtice of Her Frown,</l>
               <l>That doing no offence was forc't away</l>
               <l>With Her dear Lord, a cruel Fate t' obey,</l>
               <l>And Sacrifice Her Joy, Her Peace and Fame,</l>
               <l>To a curſt Branded thing without a Name?</l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:101833:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 42 -->
               <l>Down her fair face the liquid Treaſures rowld;</l>
               <l>Then taking on her ROYAL PARTNER hold,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>England farewell,</hi> She cry'd, <hi>thou hated ſhore,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And may I never ſee thy baſeneſs more!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But ſhe comes back, and nobly may deſpiſe</l>
               <l>The Pigmy Malice of her Enemies;</l>
               <l>Diſdain and Anger in Her forehead ſit,</l>
               <l>Yet both ſo calm'd and temper'd by Her Wit,</l>
               <l>That with a modeſt ſmile She ſtrives t' oppoſe</l>
               <l>Revenge, and onely pities all her foes.</l>
               <l>Return then and forgive, and may Your <hi>Name</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Charm the wide Globe, as does your HEROES <hi>Fame:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Long may ye love, and ſtill may ye appear</l>
               <l>Teeming, as to our Joy you prove this Year.</l>
               <l>Your Pregnant Veins are framing wondrous things,</l>
               <l>Oh glorious Paſſion that creates young Kings!</l>
               <l>The Illuſtrious Infant ſtruggles in the Womb,</l>
               <l>As if he knew his Royal fate to come,</l>
               <l>And ſilently mourns, that ſo long a ſpace</l>
               <l>'Twill be, e're he begins his Glorious Race:</l>
               <l>But when as the Divineſt Gift of Heaven,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Princely Babe</hi> is for our Comfort given,</l>
               <l>May every heart conſpire with every tongue</l>
               <l>T' implore his years may be renown'd and long,</l>
               <l>That he may merit his brave Fathers Name</l>
               <l>And Rival Vertue with his Mothers Fame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Methinks I ſee our great AUGUSTUS ſtand,</l>
               <l>With the fair PRINCESS ſmiling in His Hand,</l>
               <l>High Grandeur mixt with Joy adorns His Face,</l>
               <l>Whilſt bluſhing Duty Hers does ſweetly grace:</l>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:101833:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 43 -->
               <l>Their Eyes are fixt and mingling Glories ſeem,</l>
               <l>Like the Sun's Rayes Reflecting on a Jem:</l>
               <l>His Awfull Light then on His BROTHER ſhines,</l>
               <l>Who with a ſilent Modeſty inclines</l>
               <l>To hear his welcome, and with humble grace</l>
               <l>Fixing His Eyes upon His Monarch's Face,</l>
               <l>His willing Knees with Loyal duty bend</l>
               <l>To His dear <hi>King,</hi> His <hi>Brother,</hi> and His <hi>Friend,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who in His Arms do's the Lov'd Favourite hold,</l>
               <l>And ſpeaks a gracious welcome from His ſoul.</l>
               <l>Thrice happy <hi>Scotland,</hi> well didſt thou begin</l>
               <l>To make attonement for thy former ſin,</l>
               <l>When thou with Joy a Vertue didſt Embrace:</l>
               <l>By brooding Factions driven from this place,</l>
               <l>Well was the much-wrong'd <hi>Prince</hi> receiv'd by thee,</l>
               <l>And well haſt thou reform'd thy Loyalty:</l>
               <l>Yet to His Goodneſs thou thy Fame do'ſt owe,</l>
               <l>For thou hadſt faithleſs bin had he been ſo:</l>
               <l>But as the <hi>Thracian</hi> Bard, with charming ſtrains,</l>
               <l>Drew the Wild Savages from Woods and Plains,</l>
               <l>Controll'd their Brutiſh Rage where e're he came,</l>
               <l>And made the fierceſt Bears and Tigers tame;</l>
               <l>So Mighty Prince Thy Vertue did oppoſe</l>
               <l>The cloſe deſigns and Malice of thy Foes,</l>
               <l>And made a Nation, fam'd for Treachery,</l>
               <l>Bow to thy Loyal Principles and Thee,</l>
               <l>Whilſt <hi>England</hi>'s left with its <hi>King-killing</hi> Race,</l>
               <l>A Neſt of Rebels, as it ever was.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
